Shalom שלום, Shalom, boker tov בוקר טוב, Boker Tov, we pick up
on Daf Yud Amud Aleph דף י' עמוד א', Daf Yud Amud
Aleph, today's daf is Daf Yud דף י', Daf Yud, 10. Now
we are right now in a very important halachic section of Chullin
חולין, Chullin, and not even just halachic in the sense of like
the small specific details of halacha הלכה, halacha, but fundamental halachic principles
where this is the section where the Gemara גמרא Gemara explores basic
principles about how do we know how to deal with areas of
doubt and what types of halachic mechanisms
there are to deal with doubt. And the one we've established so
far is one principle of Chazakah חזקה, Chazakah, which is about status
quo, and we're going to be moving into the issue tomorrow really
about Rov רוב, Rov, about following Rov רוב. Rov. Okay, so these
are some very fundamental halachic majority. So these are fundamental halachic principles.
So yesterday what we saw is we saw the idea that you
go by Chazakah חזקה. Chazakah. If something has a status quo, the
status quo is assumed to remain unless you know otherwise. So an
animal, for example, starts with the status quo of being forbidden meat.
When an animal is alive it's forbidden, so you cannot assume that
it's kosher כשר kosher until you've done until you know that you've
done a kosher כשר kosher shechita שחיטה, shechita, which means interestingly not
just checking the knife beforehand and having an experienced person do it,
but it also means checking the simanim סימנים, simanim, the trachea and
the esophagus afterwards, inspecting them, making sure that they were done correctly.
Now that itself might only be rabbinic because obviously even though you
have to know for certain, there's still a question of what determines
for certain whether it required visual inspection just to know for certain
that you did it correctly would not necessarily be obvious, but nevertheless
that's what the Gemara גמרא Gemara said there. So that's on the
one hand, so unless you know for certain. On the other hand,
once it was shechted שחט shechted correctly and you know for certain,
there's also a status of assuming the animal was not treif טריפה,
treif, does not have treifus טריפות treifus in terms of the internal
organs and therefore if there's any question or doubt, unless you know
for certain there's a problem, it's okay. And the Gemara גמרא Gemara
dealt with that about a case of a wolf took the like
one of the heart and returned it and you didn't know if
it made a hole or not and that also really leads to
our principle which we'll see more of today and tomorrow that we
don't have to basically check the internal organs except for the lungs
where it's very likely because we assume that everything is okay unless
we know for certain otherwise. So that's using the principle of Chazakah
חזקה Chazakah and the Gemara גמרא Gemara ended the day we ended
the day yesterday with saying that that's all nice and well when
it comes to halachic issues. For halachic issues you can tell me
oh we have this principle called status quo. But when it comes
to real world questions like health issues, sakana סכנה sakana issues, status
quo doesn't mean anything. There there's just a very simple question: what's
the percentage likelihood there's a problem or not? Okay, it doesn't matter
what the status was beforehand. So if it's a real question of
what is the real fact found around and it's something that's not
about just giving it a halachic status but a real issue like
a health issue, a sakana סכנה sakana issue, there the Gemara גמרא
Gemara says obviously we're going to use a different standard. The principle
of Chazakah חזקה Chazakah is not relevant. But for halacha הלכה halacha
we could say we don't just go by percentages, we have a
principle called status quo called Chazakah חזקה. Chazakah. So that was yesterday.
The principle of Chazakah חזקה Chazakah whether it be lenient or strict.
We're going to continue with that principle today and deal with questions
about what happens when you see that there is a problem and
then tomorrow we're going to move to another principle called Rov רוב.
Rov. So some very fundamental Gemaras גמרא Gemaras that we are dealing
with. So let's take a look now, we pick up on Yud
Amud Aleph י' עמוד א' Yud Amud Aleph after it said shma
mina שמע מינה. shma mina. Tnan hatam תנן התם, Tnan hatam, 1,
2, 3, 4, 5, 6 lines or 7 lines from the top,
beginning of the line where there is an asterisk. So because in
this discussion about sakana סכנה, sakana, about health, we discussed the issue
about exposed liquids and concerns that snakes drank from them, we're going
to first wrap that up. Tnan hatam תנן התם, Tnan hatam, so
we taught over there:
Gimmel mashkin assurim mishum gilluy ג' משקין אסורין משום גילוי. Gimmel mashkin
assurim mishum gilluy. Three types of liquids are forbidden if they're left
exposed because you're afraid that snakes drank from them and they left
over some poison: mayim v'yayin v'chalav מים ויין וחלב, mayim v'yayin v'chalav,
water, wine, and milk. Kama yishtu v'yei'asru כמה ישהו ויאסרו, Kama yishtu
v'yei'asru, how long do you have to leave them unattended?
How long do you have to leave them unattended in order that
they should be forbidden? K'dei she'yeitzei harachash mimakom karov v'yishteh כדי שיצא
הרחש ממקום קרוב וישתה. K'dei she'yeitzei harachash mimakom karov v'yishteh. So the
rachash רחש, rachash, the crawling thing, the slithery thing, meaning here the
snake, it's interesting that it uses the phrase rachash רחש, rachash, will
be able to pop out from a nearby place and drink. Meaning,
so you know, not that long. You have to assume what's the
likelihood that it's got a hole right here in the ground right
near to where I am, if I just turn my back a
second there's enough time for it to slither out of its hole.
Slithery would be a good translation for rachash רחש. rachash. Slither out
of a hole, drink and drink. So the Gemara גמרא Gemara says,
v'kama makom karov וכמה מקום קרוב, V'kama makom karov, how nearby is
nearby? Amar Rabbi Yitzchak brei d'Rav Yehuda אמר רבי יצחק בריה דרב
יהודה, Amar Rabbi Yitzchak brei d'Rav Yehuda, k'dei she'yeitzei mitachat ozen kli
v'yishteh כדי שיצא מתחת אוזן כלי וישתה. K'dei she'yeitzei mitachat ozen kli
v'yishteh. You might have to assume what if there's a snake hole
right underneath the pitcher handle, assuming the pitcher is left out on
the ground, right, so maybe you're not seeing the hole because right
under the handle might it sort of blocks you from seeing directly
underneath it, there's a snake hole right there. So you have
to assume. No, well, presumably not. Then it would be if it's
somewhere under the table, to slither up the table. Okay. So the
גמרא Gemara says what? Minute? הכא חזי ליה? haka chazi lei? No,
you can't just say long enough to slither out and drink because
then if you turned back within a few seconds, if it only
had a chance to slither out and drink, you would still see
it. So if you didn't see it, obviously, that should be the
indication that it didn't happen. So the גמרא Gemara says, אלא ישתה
ויחזור לחורו. ela yishteh veyachzor lechoro. Okay, so long enough to slither
out, take a drink, and slither back into its hole. So if
you leave it unattended that long, assuming the hole is right nearby,
you've got a problem. If you look at תוספות, Tosfos, תוספות Tosfos
quotes ירושלמי, Yerushalmi, which is even presumably stricter. He says, בירושלמי מתרץ,
Beyerushalmi matretz, כחוט השערה ושפיפון שמו. kechut hasa'ara u'shfiphon shemo. First of
all, there's a type of snake that's thin as a hair, and
it's called a שפיפון. shfiphon. I don't know if it's that little
and all. I mean, there is an asp, right? An asp is
very, very thin, right? So I don't know if that, but anyway,
that's my translation of it. And he says, ורשות ניתנה לקרקע להיבקע
לפניו ולא ניתנה רשות לכלי להיבקע מפניו. v'reshus nitna lekarka lehibakeia lefanav
velo nitna reshus lakli lehibakeia mipanav. The permission is given for the
ground to crack in its presence, which basically means that even if
you don't see a hole, it can somehow get into the earth
even presumably. I mean, I'm translating a little, not literally it means
that the ground will actually crack and make a hole for it.
I'm translating it as it can sneak into a hole you can't
even see. Okay, but therefore we have to be able to catch
it. So if you have enough time for it to, assuming even
if you don't see a hole, for it to slither out from
an immediate close place, drink and slither back, then you've got a
problem. Now, this is הלכה מים מגולים. halacha mayim megulim. תוספות Tosfos
in a number of places, he doesn't discuss it here, basically says
that we don't פסקן pasken מים מגולים. mayim megulim. This is all
because they had a lot of snakes around, and we don't have
snakes around. Now, this is interesting actually because the הלכות halachos of
גילוי giluy are stated explicitly in משניות. Mishnayos. I mean, this is
like very early and הלכה halacha material. It's formulated in strict laws,
like it's אסור, assur, forbidden and all these types of things. And
nevertheless, תוספות Tosfos says, yeah, but none of it is an issue
for us. It's all based on סכנה, sakana, we don't have this
problem about snakes or it's not a problem. And that's why you
might never have heard the הלכה halacha that don't leave your drinks
unattended and you can't drink from it because as אשכנזים Ashkenazim we
don't פסקן. pasken. Nevertheless, the רמב"ם Rambam פסקן paskens it pretty straight,
and if I remember correctly, the שולחן ערוך Shulchan Aruch פסקן paskens
it for the ספרדים Sefardim pretty straight. So be interesting to know
whether ספרדי Sefardi הלכה halacha they still, you know, how they really
treat this issue about מים מגולים mayim megulim and are they strict
about it or not. But it very much parallels another issue which
you do know about another type of water, which is מים אחרונים,
mayim acharonim, where the גמרא Gemara says you wash your hands at
the end of the meal because of the salt that's left on
your fingertips. And that's because they preserved their meat heavily in salt.
Also because they did not have forks at the time of the
גמרא. Gemara. Forks were a later invention that made its way into
Europe at around the 14th century. So if you're handling meat that
is heavily salted and you are not washing your hands, then you
will touch your hands with your eyes and you will be problem.
תוספות Tosfos says it's not an issue for us. Not clear, I
once had a theory that they had already invented forks, forks had
already been introduced to France and Germany by the time תוספות Tosfos
was writing it, but so far I don't think that's correct. I'm
still going to try to prove it anyway. But nevertheless, for some
reason תוספות Tosfos says it's not because in תוספות's Tosfos day they
still did preserve their stuff with, excuse me, their meat with salt.
So I don't know why תוספות Tosfos feels it's not an issue.
But anyway, be that as it may, תוספות Tosfos felt maybe the
type of salt that they use or how heavily they preserved it
or whatever it was, and therefore he says we don't have to
worry about מים אחרונים. mayim acharonim. But the רמב"ם Rambam still rules
it and the שולחן ערוך Shulchan Aruch still rules it. So I
just bring these two together because it's interesting. מים אחרונים mayim acharonim
is much later, it's an Amoraic statement, it talks about a מצווה
mitzvah to wash it. By the הכא, hacha, it's even stronger הלכה
halacha language. It says אסור, assur, it gives all of these various
parameters. If you do it this way it's אסור, assur, that way
it's אסור. assur. Like there's a whole literature at the Tannaitic level
about this, and nevertheless, תוספות Tosfos basically says it's all based on
health issues which are not relevant and therefore he does away with
it. But the רמב"ם Rambam keeps all of this stuff on the
books. Yes.
Snakes only eat, they don't drink.
Yeah, that's a problem. As we said, as we said, the גמרא,
Gemara, I didn't make that specific point yesterday, but, yeah, it obviously
does not make sense that, and even if it does drink, it
doesn't let out poison when it drinks. It only lets out poison
when it actually, you
know, exactly. What'd you say?
Most snakes aren't poisonous.
Well, but that's beside the point, even if some were. No, the
problem is that presumably the גמרא Gemara was observing a reality that
certain liquids left, you know, exposed to the air, you get sick
afterwards. Now, that has to do more with contamination issues than snakes'
issues. Right, maybe milk also because it got sour or whatever, but
other types of things just for general like contaminants, you know, and
maybe rust or other types of issues if it was left in
metal pots or so. But anyway, presumably the גמרא Gemara was seeing
certain facts but just giving a wrong explanation for them. But yes,
that's a question as
well, and it's not...
If they drink wine?
I'm not so sure. I'm not so
sure. If you're living in a pre-empirical period, the types of assumptions
you make or what you refer, I was again just to draw
on some recent experiences when I was in Senegal. There you go.
We looked at a woman's health output where they started the way
they introduced to these midwives, they started teaching them. People had real
experiences being midwives for traditions for hundreds of years. But they introduced
some Western medicine and they learned certain things. So for example, they
learned that the relationship
between, trying to remember what it was said that they didn't realize
the relationship until after they learned Western medicine which for us would
have seemed obvious. It was something like the relationship between
some types of issues about the health of the mother and the
health of the child or bleeding afterwards and that it's like if
there was bleeding afterwards they didn't realize it had to do because
of how they delivered the child. Some types of things which for
us would have just been quite obvious. What are you talking about?
Of course if you deliver a child in this type of a
way and there's bleeding afterwards there's a relationship there. But if you
don't know Western science and you live in a sort of a
pre-empirical type of
a mode then you don't draw certain connections.
So I think that that's I don't think necessarily things would have
been obvious even if you live with snakes to know what types
of things are related and not related. רבקה, Rivka, did you have
a question?
I'm just wondering who decides which הלכות Halakhot get tossed because they
don't apply anymore. Yeah.
So that is an excellent question as well.
The general principle is that even though the reason changed the הלכה
Halakha doesn't change. Now, if it's something that specifically is around health,
it's actually quite interesting because there's other issues around health that the
רמב״ם Rambam readily does away with. Anything about medical remedies in the
גמרא. Gemara. More than that when the גמרא Gemara says you can't
eat fish and meat because of a health issue and it also
uses the phrase אסור, asur, the רמב״ם Rambam doesn't bring it down
because presumably he thought that the science was wrong. So specifically in
areas about
health, specifically in areas of health you could say those are never
really like fully הלכה Halakha the same way other things are. Those
are basically health statements and those change more. But the רמב״ם Rambam
himself is inconsistent about that like in the cases I just mentioned.
The other issue for תוספות Tosafot to keep aware of which some
recent scholars have made a mistake is they say, Oh look, תוספות
Tosafot says that basically this thing is based on a reason and
therefore it no longer applies. So we can basically say that we
can always assume that based on the reason it no longer applies.
The thing is that תוספות Tosafot almost always said that starting from
the fact that it was not already not practiced. And he was
trying to reconcile the fact that the law wasn't practiced in his
community with the fact that the גמרא Gemara says you're supposed to
do it. So in order to reconcile he said, Oh, we have
to assume that this law was only based on certain circumstances and
when those circumstances aren't around the law isn't around. So that's basically
תוספות's Tosafot approach which is a general אשכנזי Ashkenazic approach and also
more of a community rabbi approach, which is that you start with
some assumption that what the community is doing is maybe correct and
try to find a way to resolve it rather than try to
find a way to say that what people are doing is wrong.
But so that's another factor that often gets ignored. But you're right,
the parameters are not always clear but within תוספות Tosafot it starts
also from the fact on the ground from what people were doing.
If people were doing it, if people
were keeping מים מגולים, Mayim Megulim, you would not find a תוספות,
Tosafot, I don't care, I will put out a challenge, I don't
think you can find in all of ש״ס Shas a תוספות Tosafot
that says although everybody keeps this law since the reason no longer
applies we don't have to keep it anymore. תוספות Tosafot is not
saying that. תוספות Tosafot is saying why are we not doing this?
Oh, it must be that this law is based on this reason
and because the reason isn't relevant anymore therefore. So he is starting
from the fact that it's not being observed. Okay.
With regards to the empirical assumptions you mentioned before, I think that
applies, I would guess that applies when if you have a powerful
explanation for something that is supernatural or something like that, then it's
harder to replace it with a scientific one. If you're starting from
scratch, most people understand cause and effect. But imagine somebody who was
at קריאת ים סוף Kriyat Yam Suf and you tell them, well
it was a very windy day. Like yes it was, but it
was a miracle.
So it's not that surprising but if you have a whole foundation
and a way of thinking about this.
That's a good point too. Okay, very good. Alright, so now we
go on. So that was an interesting wrap up of the issue
about danger issues, but now we continue with these basic principles of
חזקה Chazaka about how to deal with questions of doubt and resolving
issues and we have already laid the foundation of חזקה Chazaka which
we're going to continue today. So let's take a look. אתמר, Itmar,
a very classic case here.
השוחט בסכין ונמצאת פגומה. Hashochet besakin venimtset peguma. You slaughtered with a
knife and now you- checked the knife beforehand, we've already talked about
the need to check the knife prior to beginning, and if not
you have to assume that it's nicked and it's a problem, but
you did check the knife. After you finish שחט, shechted, you looked
at the knife, you looked at presumably, this is interesting, are you
presumably you're also inspecting the trachea and esophagus, the סימנים, simanim, they
also look good. That was what we were told yesterday. Okay, but
it doesn't tell us about inspecting the trachea and esophagus, it just
tells us now about inspecting the knife. And you looked at the
knife afterwards and you saw it was nicked. So when did the
nick come? Before the שחיטה shechita or after the שחיטה? shechita?
Sorry, this is a case we looked at right before the שחיטה
shechita and then we looked at it again right after. So you
just שחט shechted one animal.
Exactly. Now there's going to be other cases about other things that
might have intervened, but that's in the simplest case. It was immediately
after. Let's take a look. So אמר רב הונא, Amar Rav Huna,
so רב הונא Rav Huna says, אפילו שיבר בה עצמות כל היום
פסולה. afilu shiber bah atzamot kol hayom pesula. Even if after your
שחיטה shechita you used it for chopping bones, so obviously if you
שחט shechted one animal and then chopped bones with the knife and
you found a nick, what do you assume created the nick? Obviously
the bones. So he says even though that's the most logical assumption,
it doesn't matter. Now there's a nick, so I have to be
concerned that there was a nick when you did the שחיטה. shechita.
Okay, so אפילו שיבר בה עצמות כל היום כולה, afilu shiber bah
atzamot kol hayom kulah, even if he checked it the entire day,
פסולה, pesula, it's still invalid. חיישינן, chashinan, we're concerned שמא בעור נפגמה,
shema ba'or nifgama, maybe as you were doing the שחיטה shechita and
as the knife cut the skin of the animal, the outer skin,
that's where it got the nick. It got the nick before it
finished the first שחיטה. shechita. So that is a pretty hard to
believe, right? You're doing the שחיטה, shechita, before you finish the שחיטה
shechita it gets caught on something in the animal's neck, causes a
nick, so that by the time you finish the שחיטה shechita it's
invalid. We're going to assume that, that's a worst-case scenario, rather than
assume not only the best-case but the much more reasonable scenario that
it got the nick afterwards when you were chopping the bones. But
that's what he says. We always have to be concerned about the
worst case. רב חסדא אמר, Rav Chisda amar, and רב חסדא Rav
Chisda says, כשרה, keshera, it's
kosher. רב חסדא אמר כשרה, Rav Chisda amar keshera, שמא בעצם נפגמה.
shema be'etzem nifgama. No, because maybe it happened on the bone, and
as long as it's possible it happened on the bone, we'll assume
that it was okay when you שחט shechted the actual animal, especially
since you have something else to base it on. Now this halachic
principle is called what? We'll talk about that. This halachic principle is
called, there's a ריעותא, re'uta,
meaning that you have a חזקה, chazakah, you have a status quo,
that the knife was checked and the knife was okay. That's the
status quo of the knife. But the status quo of the animal
is it's no good, but the status quo of the knife is
that it was checked. But now there's a ריעותא. re'uta. Now you
find that now we're ten minutes after you checked it, there's a
nick in it. So that undermines your assumption that the status quo
remained. You know that the status quo actually ended at a certain
point. And now your question is, when did it end? Now that's
different than yesterday. Yesterday was we had a status quo, and if
any doubt comes about, we'll assume that the status quo remained and
that the doubt never actualized. So I had a status quo that
it wasn't a טרפה. treifa. Oh, maybe the wolf made a hole
in it. No, I'll assume that it remains kosher, I'll assume it
wasn't a טרפה, treifa, that was my status quo. So the status
quo said reject your doubt. Or I had a status quo that
it was not kosher meat. Maybe I did a good שחיטה. shechita.
Sorry, if you can't prove you did a good שחיטה, shechita, we
assume the status quo, we assume it's still not kosher. So there
the status quo said if you have a doubt, reject your doubt,
assume status quo. Here it's different. Here your status quo has changed.
The knife was okay, now it's not good. So your status quo
can't tell you it never got the nick, you see the nick.
So now the question is, can the status quo tell me assume
it remained good as long as possible? Assume that the nick only
came at the last moment. Okay, that is the question. I'm going
to give you an extreme example of this where we do this
where we say that even when there's a ריעותא re'uta we still
assume the חזקה chazakah until the last possible moment. I'm reading from
the Torah and I come to a word and the letter has
a crack in it and it's not a kosher letter. So I
take out a new ספר תורה Sefer Torah and I redo that
עליה. aliyah. Why do I redo just that עליה aliyah on שלישי?
shlishi? Why don't I have to do the whole קריאה? keriah? Because
obviously the letter had a crack in it when I started reading
the Torah, and therefore the whole קריאה keriah was no good because
the whole ספר תורה Sefer Torah was no good. No, we assume
the crack occurred just in the last minute. Okay, it didn't occur
on the previous עליה, aliyah, it occurred just in the last minute,
and therefore I only have to redo the last עליה. aliyah. Why?
Yes, I mean there are other things you rely on as well,
but a שיטת הרמב"ם, shitat HaRambam, whatever, but anyway, so that might
be other factors, but that's an example where it was known to
be good at a time, now it's not good, do you use
the חזקה—it's chazakah not telling you a problem didn't occur, you know
a problem did occur—do you use the חזקה chazakah to say that
the problem occurred only at the last minute? Okay, so here's the
question. Here it's even stronger because you have a very obvious thing
that you can connect the nick to: the breaking of bones. And
so that's two good reasons to say the problem occurred at the
end. Number one, you had your חזקה chazakah to push it off,
and number two, you used it to break bones, which is a
more reasonable. And nevertheless, the first opinion says, no, you have to
always be concerned once your חזקה Chazakah is, you see that it
ended, you have to be concerned all the way back that now
everything is thrown into doubt. Okay, so that's the question about how
does חזקה Chazakah work when there's a ריעותא? reuta? We're obviously not
done. Michael, what's your question?
I think we're going to get into this. Let's say I'm שוחט
shochet ten animals.
We're going to get into that.
Why wouldn't a nick invalidate the שחיטה? shechitah?
Because it's concerned and instantly so. So again, because because the גמרא
Gemara assumes, I mean whatever, that if there's a nick, then it
does an action of tearing rather than an action of cutting.
Okay, so it'll, you know, so. So what? So it assumes that,
yeah, part of the laws of שחיטה shechitah is that it has
to be cut by the sharpness of the knife and not torn.
And that if there's a nick, then it tears rather than cuts.
That's just one of the...
Does it make a difference to the animal?
Okay, but not everything... I mean we like to say that שחיטה
shechitah one of the things about שחיטה shechitah is that the animal
doesn't suffer, but again, whether that's whether that's true or not, that's
not how you determine whether it's כשר kosher or not by when
you שוהה, shoheh, when you pause a second, when you apply a
little bit of pressure or whatever. We don't say, oh did it
cause suffering or not suffering? That whole idea about the issue of
suffering of the animals, which is not you're not going to find
that in the גמרא Gemara in חולין Chulin in discussing שחיטה. shechitah.
I mean we did find it yesterday about רבי'ס Rebbi's white mule,
but you're not going to basically find it in the גמרא Gemara
in חולין Chulin in discussing שחיטה. shechitah. The גמרא Gemara just deals
with here are the criteria, here's how it's done, if you do
it in a different way it's not good and so on. So
any explanation you give is an after-the-fact explanation that doesn't factor in
to determining the parameters of what makes כשר שחיטה. kosher shechitah.
So you're saying that's not a goal, is not to eliminate suffering.
I can't say if it's a goal or not a goal, but
it's not something that determines the הלכתי halachic parameters of שחיטה. shechitah.
You might want to say in the macro, yes, the laws of
שחיטה shechitah are devised in order to minimize the suffering, but those
are not in the case-by-case and in the micro determining, you know,
the exact parameters that we consider that question. You don't see it
anywhere that we consider that question.
Any system will have a case where its goals are not being
well served because... But that's a goal.
The
גמרא Gemara never discusses טעמי המצוות. ta'amei hamitzvot. In what הלכתי halachic
discussion does the question about and what is the טעמי המצוות ta'amei
hamitzvot and how does that factor in? Right, that's usually a whole
separate endeavor that you'll find in the ספר החינוך Sefer HaChinuch and
in the רמב"ם Rambam and in other types... you don't find that
in mostly in the narrow הלכתי halachic discussion.
You could say with the liquids uncovered that there would be a
סכנה.
sakanah. Yeah, that's that's not a biblical... Right, that's true, that's true.
Right, yes, but that's a biblical that's not a biblical מצוה. mitzvah.
When you're dealing with biblical מצוות, mitzvot, now here again these get
questions of דרשינן טעמא דקרא, darshinan ta'ama de'kra, לא דרשינן טעמא דקרא.
la darshinan ta'ama de'kra. You know, there are some times it plays
a factor but by and large the גמרא Gemara ignores, not because
it's not saying that's not a reason to give for שחיטה, shechitah,
but in its הלכתי halachic deliberations largely brackets questions about what are
the reasons. Okay, let's continue.
So now the גמרא Gemara says like this. I actually recently wrote
an article about that specifically around צער בעלי חיים tza'ar ba'alei chayim
in the recent Saul Berman festschrift that the ישיבה Yeshiva put out.
So if you want you could see my article there where I
talk about when when those reasons of מצוות mitzvot are factored in
and what types of parameters and so on. Okay, so let's take
a look. The גמרא Gemara says like this.
Okay,
בשלמא Bishlama רב הונא, Rav Huna, כשמעתיה. kishmateih. So the גמרא Gemara
actually thinks that רב הונא'ס Rav Huna's position makes more sense because
we had said yesterday that רב הונא Rav Huna said that an
animal has a חזקה chazakah of being not כשר kosher until you
know for certain it was good. So here there's a doubt, there's
a doubt, so you don't know for certain anymore, so it's going
to be not good. אלא רב חסדא מאי טעמא? Ela Rav Chisda
mai ta'ama? Why does רב חסדא Rav Chisda say you can assume
the knife was okay?
So אמר לך, amar lach, רב חסדא Rav Chisda will say to
you there's a good reason here: עצם ודאי פוגם, etzem vadai pogem,
because a bone will definitely cause a nick, או ספק פוגם ספק
לא פוגם, o safek pogem safek lo pogem, whether the skin of
the animal will cause a nick is a very big question. So
הוי ספק וודאי, havei safek vevadai, there's another הלכתי halachic principle, not
a principle of חזקה, chazakah, but a principle of ספק וודאי, safek
vevadai, doubt and certainty. ואין ספק מוציא מידי וודאי, ve'ein safek motzi
miyedei vadai, a maybe does not remove from the idea of definite.
You know, like anybody who's had kids, "well maybe this, but maybe
that, but maybe that," so you can maybe from here until tomorrow.
Okay, but if we have a right just go to sleep.
But if
we have a definite reason explanation, we have a very clear explanation
of why this happened, then what point is it to speculate about
some other far-reaching possibility? Okay, so now again it's a question whether
the גמרא Gemara literally means that the bone definitely causes the nick.
Maybe it does mean that. So, or maybe it just means it's
much more likely. But either way, clearly a nick is much more
likely to have been caused by the bone or was definitely caused
by the bone, so I'm not going to worry that it was
also caused by the skin and it happened at an earlier stage.
That's why. רב חסדא Rav Chisda says makes a lot of sense.
Okay, so מתיב רבא לסיועיה לרב הונא. motive Rava l'siyayei l'Rav Huna.
So רבא Rava asks the following question to try to support רב
הונא's Rav Huna position
that it is a problem.
So someone's more like asking a question on the other position.
Right, he asks on the other to support רב הונא. Rav Huna.
So טבל ועלה ונמצא עליו דבר חוצץ. taval v'ala v'nimtza alav davar
chotzetz. Somebody goes to the מקוה mikvah and afterwards they get up
from the מקוה mikvah and this happens often sometimes that, you know,
a woman will come home from the מקוה mikvah and say oh
after I came home I saw that I had some dirt under
my fingers or, you know, and I don't know, did I do,
did I clean it before I went to the מקוה mikvah after
I went to the מקוה? mikvah? I forget. Okay, so you found
that there was some חציצה chatzitza on your body after going to
the מקוה. mikvah. Notice by the way it's in the masculine because
here the phenomenon of going to the מקוה mikvah is not limited
to a woman who is a נדה, niddah, it was, you know,
anybody who was concerned about טומאה וטהרה tuma v'tahara at that time.
Okay, you found on yourself something that is חוצץ, chotzetz, he found
on himself. אף על פי שנתעסק באותו המין כל היום כולו לא
עלתה לו טבילה. af al pi she-nit'asek b'oto hamin kol hayom kulo
lo alta lo tvila. So it's just like breaking of the bones.
Here is a guy that after he goes to the מקוה, mikvah,
he goes out to his construction site and he works in cement,
and then he comes home and he finds that he's got cement
all under his fingernails. So now, if you're smart, after you get
out of the מקוה, mikvah, you'll inspect your body and you'll see
right after the מקוה, mikvah, oh, I'm totally clean, I'm fine, I
know it was good. But you forgot to check yourself after going
to the מקוה, mikvah, you worked on your construction site, and then
you found on yourself, guess what, cement under your fingernails when you
got home. So the הלכה halacha is, even though you were dealing
with cement the whole day after the מקוה, mikvah, your טבילה tvila
is not good, because you see on yourself a חציצה chatzitza now
and we don't, and therefore we have to be concerned that that
חציצה chatzitza was on your body when you were in the מקוה
mikvah itself. Okay, כל היום כולו לא עלתה לו טבילה, kol hayom
kulo lo alta lo tvila, the טבילה tvila is not good, עד
שיאמר ברי לי, ad sheyomar bari li, I am absolutely certain
שלא היה עלי קודם לכן, she-lo haya alai kodem lachen, meaning either
I checked myself a second before going into the מקוה, mikvah, so
I know that it wasn't on my body because I checked, or
I checked myself when I came out. But if you did not
know for, can't say that for certain, you cannot attribute it to
the working of the cement afterwards and you have to concern yourself
that maybe it was on your body beforehand. So this seems to
be an exactly parallel case, right? You had a חזקה, chazaka, presumably
you did check yourself at one time earlier in the day before
going to the מקוה, mikvah, although it doesn't say that but we'll
presume. Now you don't know right when did this problem occur? You
cannot attribute it to the וודאי, vadai, to the working with the
cement. You have to be concerned that it occurred earlier because you
don't know for certain that at the moment of the טבילה tvila
it was okay.
There's two חזקות chazakot working against each other.
What? Oh, well that's what we're going to come back to. So
הגמרא hagemara says והכא, v'hacha, so here you see וודאי טבל, vadai
taval, you definitely went to the מקוה, mikvah, like you וודאי vadai
did a שחיטה. shchita. ספק הוה ליה ספק לא הוה ליה safek
hava lei safek lo hava lei and there's a doubt now because
of the evidence in front of your eyes. There's a question about
whether it was on your body at the moment you did the
טבילה. tvila. ואתי ספק ומוציא מידי וודאי, v'ati safek u-motzi mi-yedei vadai,
and the possibility that it was on you before is, you know,
that substitutes, takes the place of saying oh well we know it
definitely came from working with the cement. It is true, the cement
definitely could have caused it, but there's still a possibility that it
also was there earlier. So we don't just attribute it to the
cement and ignore the other possibility. So here too we won't just
attribute it to the bone and ignore the other possibility that it
was at the time of שחיטה. shchita. So that seems to be
a pretty good evidence. So what does the גמרא gemara say? So
the גמרא gemara says שאני התם דאיכא למימר העמד טמא על חזקתו.
shani hatam de-ika l'meimar ha'amed tamei al chazkato. So this is what
Michael's saying. Wait a minute, there's more than just the חזקה chazaka
of the knife. There's more than just the חזקה chazaka of not
having on you a חציצה. chatzitza. There's the fact of your personal
status was that you were טמא tamei before you went to the
מקוה. mikvah. So because you were טמא, tamei, any doubt afterwards, even
a far-fetched doubt that the cement was on you before, is enough
to get in the way of assuming that your status changed. Right,
it's what the גמרא gemara said before. You start with your חזקה
chazaka until you know for certain otherwise. So you're טמא. tamei. So
the גמרא gemara says well if that's true, say the same thing
here.
So
הכא נמי העמד בהמה על חזקתה hacha nami ha'amed behema al chazkata
and say
לא נשחטה. lo nishchata. So the גמרא gemara says okay but that's
what רב הונא Rav Huna says. רב הונא Rav Huna says and
applies the same thing by the animal. The animal is definitely starts
its life as not kosher meat. So as long as you have
the tiniest doubt, even the possibility that it got a nick earlier
rather than later, that's enough to say that you cannot assume it
was שחט shechted correctly. So you know, so the answer here is
oh you have a חזקה chazaka the knife was good. Why can't
the חזקה chazaka of the knife being checked be okay? The answer
is because you've got another חזקה chazaka that the animal was not
good, that the animal is not kosher. And therefore if you have
a slight doubt you can't change the status. Very good, that's a
nice articulation of רב הונא's Rav Huna position. How do you defend
it according to רב חסדא Rav Chisda that is not concerned about
the knife? So let's take a look. So the גמרא gemara says
הרי שחוטה לפניך. harei shchuta l'fanecha. No no, the animal here was
שחט shechted was שחט shechted so therefore we can assume the שחיטה
shchita was done correctly. We don't have to give it the status
quo of being not good. So the גמרא gemara says הכא נמי
הרי טבול לפניך. hacha nami harei tavul l'fanecha. So what? Here the
guy just went to the מקוה. mikvah. We know you did the
act. Our question still is, was the act done correctly or not
done correctly? The status quo doesn't change just cause the guy dunked,
and just cause the animal was שחט, shechted, if you have a
doubt about whether the dunking was good and you have a doubt
whether the שחיטה shechita was good. That's exactly the point. So the
גמרא Gemara says הא דאיתילד בה ריעותא. ha d'itilid bei rei-usa. No,
you can't just say he dunked because there's a question, there's a
ריעותא, rei-usa, this sort of undermining thing that you see that he
had a חציצה chatzitzah on him. So therefore we can't assume that
the status changed even though he dunked. So the גמרא Gemara says
same point here. הכא נמי הא דאיתילד בה ריעותא. hacha nami ha
d'itilid bei rei-usa. Here too there's a problem, there's a nick in
the knife. All of this is a beautiful articulation of רב הונא's
Rav Huna position. רב הונא Rav Huna says the animal starts off
not good. Therefore I'm not going to say it's good unless I'm
a hundred percent sure. You're going to tell me that the knife
was checked and that you did a שחיטה. shechita. It doesn't matter,
I have a little bit of a doubt cause I have a
nick right now. So the same thing by the טבילה. tvila. I
have a little bit of a doubt, I see a חציצה chatzitzah
and therefore that's going to get in the way once it starts
with a status of being not good. So again, how does רב
חסדא Rav Chisda who's okay with the שחיטה, shechita, how does he
differentiate that case from the case of the מקוה? mikvah? So the
גמרא, Gemara, let's see what the גמרא's Gemara answer is.
So the גמרא Gemara says, here's the difference. סכין
איתרעי בהמה לא איתרעי. sakin itra-ei behema lo itra-ei. Seems like a
very bizarre answer. No, no, he says like this. The question is
about the knife, the question isn't about the animal. So since the
animal, since the שחיטה, shechita, the animal we know had a problematic
status, but you did a good act of שחיטה shechita and you
checked the trachea and the esophagus—well the גמרא Gemara hasn't pointed that
out, I'm going to get to that.
So the גמרא Gemara says yes, you're saying, oh, but there's something
that raises a doubt. That doubt is in a formal way external
to the animal itself. That doubt is the animal is there, it
was שחט, shechted, the knife was checked beforehand. Now you have a
doubt, oh, but there was a nick in the knife. Since that
was external to the animal, I can somehow bracket it and focus
on the fact that as observed it was done correctly and the
knife was checked beforehand and everything was okay, as opposed to the
מקוה mikvah case where in the מקוה mikvah the question is the
doubt was whether the person's status was טמא tamei and the doubt
was maybe on the person himself there was a חציצה. chatzitzah. Since
that wasn't external, that was about the person himself, I can't bracket
it. I have to say can I change the person's status from
being טמא tamei to being טהור? tahor? No, because right in front
of me slapping me in the face is the fact that I
know that there was a חציצה chatzitzah on the person so I
can't sort of bracket that question. Whereas here I can bracket the
question and say as far as I know the שחיטה shechita was
done correctly because the knife was checked before. Now that seems to
be a very formalistic distinction which is really hard to explain. תוספות
Tosafot does not like it at all. תוספות Tosafot is what difference
does it make? It's actually quite an interesting תוספות Tosafot because normally
תוספות Tosafot is only bothered when there's like a contradiction with another
גמרא, Gemara, but here really תוספות Tosafot is like what difference does
it make? Right? Who cares where the question still is, do you
know for certain that everything was okay or not? Either way if
it had a nick, the שחיטה shechita wasn't good, so you can't
say, oh, we see the שחיטה shechita was good, we're going to
bracket the nick. The whole question is if there was a nick
the שחיטה shechita wasn't good. So תוספות Tosafot basically tries to say
that we really don't mean it. And what we really mean is
that in the knife case there's a double doubt. One doubt is
when did it get the nick? And the other doubt is that
even if it has a nick you might not have שחט shechted
where the nick was. If you imagine a very long knife, the
part of the knife you שחט shechted with might not have been
the part place where the nick was. Now that's not what the
גמרא Gemara is saying at all but תוספות Tosafot is reading it
in because otherwise תוספות Tosafot says the distinction doesn't make a difference.
I would have said, I also agree that the distinction seems very
formalistic and not to understand, but I would have said more what
Michael just said. Wait a minute. First of all in the case
of שחיטה shechita you presumably checked the knife right beforehand.
We never mentioned in the case of the מקוה mikvah that you
checked your body right beforehand.
That's number one. Presumably if you did check your body right beforehand,
maybe you checked it a few hours ago, but if you did
check it right beforehand, then there is no possibility that a piece
of cement magically got under your fingers from while you were standing
at the lip of the מקוה mikvah till you dunked in. So
that case you didn't check it beforehand. So that's difference number one,
is that to say that the nick occurred in that one moment
of the שחיטה shechita is very unlikely and you checked it right
beforehand. Difference number two is, and that maybe is exactly what the
גמרא Gemara meant when it said הרי שחוטה לפניך, harei shechuta lefanecha,
is that after the fact you are if we followed what the
גמרא Gemara said yesterday you inspect the trachea and the esophagus and
the evidence shows you that it looks like it was done perfectly.
If I come out of a מקוה, mikvah, just cause I'm dripping
wet doesn't show whether it was done correctly or not. Maybe I
have a חציצה chatzitzah on my body, maybe I don't. So there's
no idea of הרי טבול לפניך. harei tavul lefanecha. You can't inspect
unless you actually checked my body to see there was no חציצה.
chatzitzah. But in the שחיטה shechita case you actually could inspect and
that should give you the presumption that if there does appear If
there was a problem on the knife, it presumably happened later. Anyway,
to me that's the easier explanation than this double doubt that תוספות
Tosfos comes up with, and that maybe could even work in the
words of the גמרא, Gemara, where the גמרא Gemara says it's only
the question is about the knife, meaning a way to frame that
is, you inspected the actual שחיטה shechitah and everything looked correct. So
the fact that now you're saying, oh but maybe the knife and
maybe it was a problem that you can't see, doesn't matter. You
have direct evidence in front of you that allows you to establish
the fact that we assume the שחיטה shechitah was good. Anyway, that
the גמרא Gemara gives this distinction, it is hard to understand what
it is. I prefer my explanation of inspection. תוספות Tosfos gives his
explanation of a double doubt. Okay, so let's take a look. Oh,
I'm sorry, תוספות Tosfos also gives another explanation which isn't in the
גמרא, Gemara, no, forget it. Okay. No, no, no, no, no, because
it's not really, it doesn't distinguish it from the טבילה tevilah case.
It's another idea for something else. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says
like this.
Okay, so it's going to still try to prove it.
מיתיבי, Meisei, oh I'll ask you.
שחט את הושט ואחר כך נשמטה הגרגרת. shachat es haveshet ve'achar kach
nishmata hagargeres. So somebody שחט shechted the esophagus and then afterwards the
trachea moved from its right place. Now remember this idea is, I'm
pretty sure, I keep on getting them mixed up.
There's קנה kaneh and ושט, veshet, wasn't it?
Well no, there's the ושט veshet and the גרגרת. gargeres. גרגרת gargeres
is also a word for the קנה. kaneh. I'm pretty sure that
the גרגרת gargeres is the esophagus. Anybody there, any English? No? Does
it say which is which? I keep on getting confused.
What does it say?
The first one is
if someone severed at least the greater part of the bird's esophagus.
גרגרת gargeres is trachea.
Oh, גרגרת gargeres is trachea? Okay, I got them reversed. Okay, so
ושט veshet is esophagus and גרגרת gargeres is trachea. My mistake. Okay,
so you שחט shechted the, what did we say this was? The
esophagus. You שחט shechted the esophagus and then the trachea was in
its wrong place. Now remember I told you yesterday that at least
according to the עיטור Itur and we'll work with that assumption now,
even if one of the סימנים simanim is not in where it
normally is situated in the animal's body when the שחיטה shechitah was
being done, even if the animal is not a טריפה, treifah, that's
a פסול שחיטה. psul shechitah. That's the פסול psul called עיקור, ikkur,
which means that the סימנים simanim were not in their right place.
Okay, so you שחט shechted the, what did we say this was?
The esophagus.
You שחט shechted the esophagus and then, now this is a bird.
Okay, so this is a bird, so you don't have to שחט
shecht both סימנים, simanim, but then both סימנים simanim have to be
in the right place even though you don't have to שחט shecht
them both. Okay, and then you saw that the trachea was not
in the right place. And the question was, when did it get
to be in the wrong place? Before the שחיטה shechitah or after
the שחיטה? shechitah? If it was before the שחיטה, shechitah, the שחיטה
shechitah was invalid. If it was after the שחיטה, shechitah, it's valid.
שחט את הושט ונמצא הגרגרת שמוטה, shachat es haveshet venimtza hagargeres shmutah,
and afterwards you find that the, so you did again the, I
have to come up with a mnemonic to remember this, you did
the esophagus and then you found the trachea in the wrong place.
ואינו יודע אם קודם שחיטה נשמטה אם אחר שחיטה נשמטה. ve'eino yodeia
im kodem shechitah nishmata im achar shechitah nishmata. You don't know if
it was before or after the שחיטה, shechitah, which would determine if
the שחיטה shechitah was good or not. זה היה מעשה, zeh hayah
ma'aseh, this case occurred, ואמרו, ve'ameru, כל ספק בשחיטה פסול. kol safek
bashechitah pasul.
Any doubt about שחיטה, shechitah, you assume it's not good, which is
basically the principle yesterday, that until you're certain it's good, it's not
good. Now that's fine, that's a fifty-fifty, there's no reason to assume
more likely after than before, that makes sense. But what we're going
to say is, when they said a broad statement, any doubt is
not good, that seems to be even doubts that we have a
reason to assume really were good, unless you're certain are no good.
So כל ספק בשחיטה פסול לאתויי מאי, kol safek bashechitah pasul le'asuyei
mai, any doubt is no good, what does the any come to
include? לאו לאתויי כי האי גוונא, lav le'asuyei ki hai gavna, isn't
it coming to include even this case of using the knife to
break bones? Even if you have a good reason to assume that
the nick came later, we still have to be concerned. So the
גמרא Gemara said, לא לאתויי ספק שהספק דרס, lo le'asuyei safek shehasafek
daras, no,
it's about other types of doubts which are, you know, just reasonable
doubts like maybe I put on pressure, maybe I hesitated too long.
So any type of reasonable doubt, you know, then you can't assume
the שחיטה shechitah was good, it has a status quo of being
no good unless you're certain. But that doesn't address our case when
you used it to break bones, where you have a good explanation
of that why where it got the nick. That might be different
and that's רב חסדא Rav Chisda's position, that if you used it
to break bones then you can attribute it to the bone. So
the גמרא Gemara says ומאי שנא, umai shna, it says exactly this,
why is this case about the nick in the knife different from
those other cases? התם איתרעי ברישא בבהמה. hasam israyei be'reisha baveheimah.
Now the גמרא Gemara's answer here once again seems to be this
formalistic answer it gave before about location. There, if the question is,
did you put on pressure, did the trachea or esophagus move before
or after, the question is situated on the animal itself, either the
physical situation of the animal or the act that was done to
the animal, and therefore that gets in my way and I have
to confront that doubt and I cannot assume it was done correctly.
הכא, hacha, in our case by the knife, סכין איתרעי בהמה לא
איתרעי, sakin israyei beheima lo israyei, the locus of the question is
about the status of the knife and therefore because it's separate from
the animal I'm allowed to say, I look at the case, like
we said before, the simple reading of the גמרא Gemara is this
very formalistic explanation, because it's external to the animal I'm allowed to
assume the שחיטה shechita was done correctly and say it's okay. So
again the גמרא Gemara seems to be committed to this idea of
the locus of the problem, but here there's a much better answer.
Here the answer is because here you broke bones with the knife
and therefore there's a better explanation of where it got the nick.
But the גמרא Gemara seems at least in the last two answers
that some of this is very formalistic about the physical location of
the doubt. And the גמרא's Gemara not yet done, let's go on.
והלכתא, V'hilchata, the הלכה halacha is כוותיה דרב כהנא, kevastei de-Rav Kahana,
we rule like רב כהנא Rav Kahana that the שחיטה shechita is
no good כשלא שיבר בעצם, kshe-lo shiber be-etzem, when you didn't break
in bones. If you didn't break bones and now you have a
nick, you have to assume question maybe the nick was when the
שחיטה shechita was taking place. והלכתא כוותיה דרב חסדא, V'hilchata kevastei de-Rav
Chisda, on the other hand we rule like רב חסדא Rav Chisda
that the שחיטה shechita was good כששיבר בעצם, kshe-shiber be-etzem, when you
broke bones. So actually we thought the whole debate was just when
you broke bones, but the גמרא's Gemara going to say no, no,
no, they really were debating both cases and we will rule like
רב חסדא Rav Chisda that if you actually used it to break
bones afterwards you can attribute it to that, that's much more likely
than assuming the problem came earlier. So now the גמרא Gemara has
to clarify, now the גמרא Gemara says מכלל דרב חסדא אף על
גב דלא שיבר בעצם, Michlal de-Rav Chisda af al gav delo shiber
be-etzem, so this sounds like רב חסדא Rav Chisda would be so
lenient to say that even if you didn't break bones you can
assume the nick came later. But if you didn't break bones אלא
במאי איפגם, ela be-mai ipgam, where did it get its nick? Right?
If you just did a simple שחיטה shechita and found a nick
afterwards, it sounds like רב חסדא Rav Chisda himself would say that
you can assume that the nick came later. What do you mean
later? Where did it get the nick if not when שוחט-ing? shochet
So the גמרא Gemara says אימא בעצם דמפרקת איפגם, eima be-etzem de-mifrekes
ipgam, no, maybe it got the nick at the end of the
שחיטה. shechita. It got the nick when the knife you finished cutting
through the trachea and esophagus and you hit the you hit the
spine. Right, so in that that's where it got the nick and
it didn't get the nick in the skin, it got the nick
at the at the end of the שחיטה, shechita, the spine. So
so now what we have is the following. We have that we've
framed the debate at extremes. רב חסדא Rav Chisda says I will
always go if you check the knife, the knife has a חזקה
chazaka of being good. I'm going to always assume that even when
a problem pops up it occurred at the last possible minute. Okay,
so רב חסדא Rav Chisda says I'll always say the knife was
good, the problem occurred at the last possible minute, it occurred at
the end of the שחיטה shechita even if you didn't break bones.
It's the ספר תורה Sefer Torah case. רב הונא Rav Huna is
the opposite. רב הונא Rav Huna says if I see a problem
now it undermines the חזקה chazaka and I have to be concerned
that the problem was at the very beginning. And the גמרא Gemara
splits its vote. The גמרא Gemara says in a normal case we'll
rule like רב הונא. Rav Huna.
Once you see that the status quo has changed and the knife
has a nick, I have to be concerned that that nick might
have been there at the beginning. But if I have a good
thing to to attribute it to, I have a ודאי vaday thing
that would have caused the nick, then I'm going to attribute it
to that thing and not be concerned that maybe it came earlier.
So if you broke bones, then I'll attribute it to that thing.
But otherwise as a general rule, if right now the status quo
has changed, there's a problem, if I don't have something definite to
attribute it to, I'm going
to have to be concerned that all the way back that maybe
it occurred at an earlier stage. How does it deal with like
the ספר תורה Sefer Torah we'll get to that in a minute.
How does it deal with like the ספר תורה Sefer Torah case
I mentioned earlier? Again remember there's another reason here to be strict,
which is the animal starts with a חזקה chazaka status quo of
being not kosher. So that also makes us have to really work
against that status quo when you so it again this doesn't tell
you a general principle like in our ספר תורה Sefer Torah case
where you just have one question, was the ספר תורה Sefer Torah
kosher or not? It's not like something started not kosher and you're
trying to change its state. So there you might be able to
assume the problem occurred at the last possible minute. So again the
basic topic of discussion today is what is the story with a
status quo when it changes? When do we assume that change occurred?
So here we're saying that if you're trying to use this to
change something else's status quo, then you have to be concerned about
the worst case. Okay, unless again like there's something definite to attribute
it to. But if you're just trying to use this in a
vacuum it's not clear maybe you could assume that the problem occurred
later rather than earlier. Okay, that's the rule. Now if you take
a look actually at there's an interesting רש"י Rashi here, top רש"י
Rashi of the page, והלכתא כרב הונא, v'hilchata ke-Rav Huna,
רש"י Rashi says דחיישינן לעור de-chaishinan l'or that unless you broke bones
we're going to assume that it got a nick on the skin
and the שחיטה shechita is no good. And רש"י Rashi just throws
in an interesting line here, he says ועל ידי היה מעשה, v'al
yadai haya ma'aseh, this actually occurred to me once, you know, whenever
that question happened they found a nick in the knife after the
שחיטה. shechita. והורה לי רבינו יעקב ברבי יצחק בעוף
לאיסור, ve-horeh li Rabbeinu Ya'akov berabbi Yitzchak be-of l'issur, and the case
was about birds, interesting, like is he suggesting that maybe we would
have been more lenient if it was by בהמה? behema? I don't
know. Anyway it says and we פסק-ed pasken so to speak, you
know, I got a פסק psak that it should be אסור assur
because based on this גמרא Gemara you find a nick and unless
you've been breaking bones you have to assume that the nick occurred
earlier rather than later. Okay so that's the ruling of the גמרא
Gemara but
now...
It sounded like oh I know רב אשי Rav Ashi did the
שחיטה shechita but it might mean it might mean that the question
came to him and he referred it to his רבי Rebbe at
the time. I don't think it means he was a שוחט, shochet,
okay. It's like the question of was he really a vintner? חיים
סולובייצ'יק Chaim Soloveitchik says that everybody assumes רש"י Rashi was a vintner
because in one תשובה teshuva רש"י Rashi says I have to rush
now because the time is coming to press the grapes. So everybody
assumes he was a
vintner. חיים סולובייצ'יק Chaim Soloveitchik says anybody that knows anything about how
they made wine in France knows that there's only like a two-week
window where you can actually press the grapes to turn it into
wine and the whole community would turn out to help in the
process. He says it's like רש"י Rashi had written on ערב פסח
Erev Pesach you have to excuse me I have to go bake
the מצות matzos that we would infer from that that רש"י Rashi
was a baker. So I don't think you can infer from this
that רש"י Rashi was a שוחט, shochet, okay, but anyway the question
was raised for him. All right, anyway now the גמרא Gemara goes
on.
הוה עובדא Havah uvda talking about the case occurred, so now the
גמרא Gemara is going to talk about some cases. הוה עובדא Havah
uvda there so such a case occurred that a nick was found
in the knife after שחיטה shechita וטרף רב יוסף איתליסר חיוותא v'taraf
Rav Yosef atlaisar chivasa and רב יוסף Rav Yosef טרף trafe up
thirteen animals. They started שחיטה, shechita, they found a nick at the
knife at the end. He so said well maybe the nick occurred
way at the beginning because that's sort of like what the גמרא
Gemara is saying unless you have the breaking of bones to attribute
it to you have to assume worst case. So even if he
שחט shachted thirteen animals and then found the nick it's all a
problem.
Says the גמרא Gemara כמאן כמאן k'man k'man who is this like?
כרב הונא k'Rav Huna ואפילו בקמייתא. v'afillu b'kamaisa. Sounded like it's רב
הונא Rav Huna and even the first animal he said was no
good because even רב הונא Rav Huna even if you find in
the first animal you assume the nick occurred at the earliest possible
minute.
So the גמרא Gemara
says לא lo not necessarily maybe כרב חסדא k'Rav Chisda ולבר מקמייתא
ul'bar mikamaisa except for the first animal meaning רב חסדא Rav Chisda
says that you assume
I'll tell you where it got the nick? It got the nick
he said not from the skin it maybe got the nick from
the
backbone when it was שחט. shachting. Okay but then the גמרא Gemara
says so let's assume it got it from the first backbone so
even if we assume like רב חסדא Rav Chisda the first animal
is okay but afterwards all the other animals are no good. Okay
now that's not exactly what we've been expecting from רב חסדא. Rav
Chisda. We've been expecting from רב חסדא Rav Chisda to interpret it
in the way that is the best case scenario right? Not just
oh it's more likely the backbone than the skin. If that were
all he was saying more likely the backbone than the skin then
you'd have to have problems after the first animal. But our assumption
is that רב חסדא Rav Chisda is trying to interpret a best
case scenario so the גמרא Gemara is going to get there. Okay
ואי בעית אימא v'ee ba'is ayma or if you want the גמרא
Gemara says לעולם כרב הונא l'olam k'Rav Huna you're right it is
like רב הונא Rav Huna who says worst case scenario. דאי כרב
חסדא d'ee k'Rav Chisda if it was like רב חסדא Rav Chisda
מכדי מתלי תלינן michdee matlee taleenan now this phrase תלינן taleenan means
we sort of attribute it means we don't know what it is
so we're going to conveniently assume the best case scenario. So since
רב חסדא Rav Chisda is based on making an assumption for the
best case scenario so therefore אטו במפרקתא דקמייתא איתגם attu b'mifarkasa d'kamaisa
itgam why should I try to say that it happened at the
backbone of your first animal? דילמא במפרקתא דבתרייתא איתגם dilma b'mifarkasa d'basraisa
itgam
maybe it got the nick in the backbone of the last animal?
So again רב חסדא Rav Chisda who is more influenced by the
חזקה chazaka that the knife was checked and since the knife was
checked I'm going to assume the problem occurred later rather than sooner
is going to say that all your animals are okay and I'll
attribute it to the backbone of the last animal. Okay so now
we are consistent though with if you haven't been breaking bones you're
going to have to טרף trafe it up. So for the by
and large we rule like רב הונא Rav Huna and all the
animals are טרף. trafe.
Why? Because רב חסדא Rav Chisda is more...
Yeah רב חסדא Rav Chisda is definitely more lenient and based on
his use of חזקה chazaka correct. So now אמר ליה רב אחא
בריה דרבא לרב אשי amar leh Rav Acha breih d'Rava l'Rav Ashi
so רב אחא
בריה דרבא Rav Acha breih d'Rava
said to רב אשי Rav Ashi רב כהנא משיך בדיקותא בין כל
חד וחד. Rav Kahana mashich bedikuta beyn kol chad v'chad. רב כהנא
Rav Kahana that's a pretty good prudent policy especially
if you פסקן pasken like רב הונא. Rav Huna. Check your knife
after every animal. So therefore if you find a nick the worst
case is you'll טרף trafe up the most recent animal but then
you'll switch your knife okay rather than waiting till the end and
טרף trafe up everything. כמאן k'man who is that like? כרב הונא
k'Rav Huna למיפסל קמייתא l'mifsal kamaisa so
therefore by checking it between each animal you will טרף trafe up
the one the prior one but you can
go the other way around with that?
Well wait a minute you'll טרף trafe up the prior one and
therefore but the later ones will be okay because you'll be able
to change your knife or sharpen it. So the גמרא Gemara says
that sounds like you're going the גמרא Gemara says maybe not לא
lo כרב חסדא ולאכשורי בתרייתא k'Rav Chisda ul'achshuri basraisa maybe it's like
רב חסדא Rav Chisda but according to the way we interpreted רב
חסדא Rav Chisda earlier not the best case scenario and it happens
at the backbone of the last animal but maybe we'll assume like
רב חסדא Rav Chisda it happens. it occurs at the backbone of
the first animal. So maybe it's like רב חסדא *Rav Chisda* and
you're checking it because even according to רב חסדא *Rav Chisda* anything
after the first animal he'll also admit is a problem. Again, if
רב חסדא *Rav Chisda*'s not saying it occurs at the very last
minute, just it occurs at the end of the first animal. So
maybe that's why we're doing it. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says
אי הכי *Ee hachi* and here's very interesting, it gets to the
issue of checking the knife, תיבעי נמי בדיקת חכם *Tzivai nami bedikas
chacham*. If the point of checking this is not just to see
whether what I've already done is okay, which would be the focus
for רב הונא *Rav Huna*, but it's actually to make sure that
what, but if, like רב חסדא *Rav Chisda*, what I've done is
definitely okay, it's now a question of can I, is it smart
to continue? So if you're checking the knife to see if you
can continue, then that's like the normal checking of a knife that
gets done before you start שחיטה *shechita* in general. Now what did
we learn about who checks the knife? You bring it to the
sage to check. So if you're checking between each animal not to
see just whether what you've done was okay, that is definitely going
to be okay, but to see if you can continue to the
next animal, why don't you have to show it, show it to
a sage?
Maybe he's a sage, like we said yesterday.
So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says yeah we don't need to say
that, עד אחד נאמן באיסורין *Eid echad ne'eman b'issurin*. You don't need
to go to a sage, you can check your own knife.
Because we trust one witness for issues of כשרות *kashrus*, right, you
trust your butcher, the husband trusts their wives, and wives trust their
husbands about where they bought the meat and what they did with
it. You trust people in issues of כשרות *kashrus*, so you can
trust the שוחט *shochet* that he checked his own knife. So the
גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says אי הכי *Ee hachi*, if that's true, מעיקרא
נמי לא *Mei-ikara nami lo*? Why from the very beginning do you
ever have to show your knife to a חכם *chacham*, if we
can trust the שוחט *shochet*? So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says no,
that's not for a הלכה *halachic* reason, that's for like a כבוד
*kavod* reason. אמר רבי יוחנן *Amar Rabbi Yochanan*, רבי יוחנן *Rabbi Yochanan*
says לא אמרו להראות סכין לחכם *lo amru l'har'ot sakin l'chacham*, they
only said you have to show it to the sage, not for
הלכה *halachic* trustability, if that's a word, trust, אלא מפני כבודו של
חכם *elah mipnei kvodo shel chacham*. To give honor to the sage
to show that it's all taking place under his authority and that
you acknowledge his authority and so on. So that's why it is
done and but now that you do it once, you do it
at the, a new sage comes to town, all the שוחטים *shochtim*
line up and show him their knives, but after you do it
from then on in you're trusted to check your own. Oh really?
So you don't have to do it like daily or whatever?
Right, right, correct. Okay, so therefore, so anyways, so now we have
established that whether certainly according to רב הונא *Rav Huna*, maybe according
to רב חסדא *Rav Chisda* based on when he gets concerned if
you do a row of animals, but you should check your knife
between each animal because then at the worst case if you do
have a nick, you'll only טרף *traif* up one animal and you
won't טרף *traif* up like the גמרא *Gemara*'s case of thirteen animals.
Okay.
So wait, so what do we say in the end, are we
going to get to that?
That is the end of this discussion. The end is we rule
like רב הונא *Rav Huna*, and if you have a חזקה chazaka
*chazaka* and then there's a ריעותא *rei'asa*, a problem, so even though
we do not assume it occurred at the last possible minute, we
assume that it occurred earlier, but again, that is only here where
you're trying to change the status of the animal from being not
כשר *kosher* and use your knife and the חזקה chazaka *chazaka* of
the knife to change the status of the animal. There, we assume
more of a worst-case scenario rather than
a best-case scenario and the problem occurred at the end. And even
here the גמרא *Gemara* says if you were breaking bones with it,
you can also attribute it to the breaking bones, but that's an
exceptional case. Yes, Charlie.
When they brought in the comparison to מקוה *Mikvah*, that would seem
to be a little different because מקוה *Mikvah* is often dealing with
issues that would be a potential איסור כרת *issur kareis* for נדה
*niddah* or for eating קדשים *kodshim* whereas eating non simply eating non-kosher
food is an ordinary biblical prohibition.
Yeah. And I keep hearing we're so strict on נדה *niddah*, we're
so strict on חמץ *chametz* because there's an איסור כרת *issur kareis*
involved, but the גמרא *Gemara* doesn't mention that at all.
Right. Well, for these types of things it's not making those distinctions.
I don't know what to say other than that sometimes the weight
of the prohibition matters, but very often in these principles of using
חזקה chazaka, *chazaka* and using רוב rov. *rov* or whatever they are
across the board without attention to how strict or not strict something
is. There are sometimes you find distinctions but right, not as a
general rule.
So I mean it is true, but the גמרא *Gemara* does not
always attend to that in particular about these sort of global principles.
But at the end of the day, we say if you're שוחט
*shechting* thirteen animals and then you discover this nick in the knife
at the end of the day, or wherever it is, any animal
after the first one all are bad including the first one. Yep.
Unless you were breaking bones, in which case then everything was good
until you were breaking bones and everything afterwards is bad.
Well, of course, once there's a nick, there's a nick, right. Okay,
so now the גמרא *Gemara* continues.
And
he didn't check the קנה וושט *kaneh and veshet* and all that.
That's the funny thing is that it doesn't discuss here, I was
saying that to integrate yesterday's דף *daf*. Okay, the גמרא *Gemara* here
does not discuss checking the trachea and esophagus and you could actually
say that was a different opinion and even if we wind up
ruling
that, that was
a... I'd have to see. The interesting thing is these two סוגיות
*sugyot* take place one דף *daf* after the next and they're not
in conversation with one another. We mentioned that that was what we
said yesterday. It never came up in this גמרא *Gemara* and one
could obviously argue that if you're directly checking it that that should
weigh in on determining what had happened. So I'd have to see
if that gets discussed. I don't know offhand. Okay, but the גמרא
*Gemara* it's important to note that the גמרא *Gemara* not every סוגיא
*sugya* exists side by side. They don't always assume one another. So
just because we had the other סוגיא *sugya* yesterday doesn't mean it's
being assumed in this discussion.
Like רש"י *Rashi* and חומש *Chumash*.
Right, right. Okay, so now we move on with another, now we
move on, now that we've been discussing for a day and a
half about חזקה chazaka *hazakah*, now we try to learn, ask the
question about whether we know the principle of חזקה chazaka. *hazakah*. So
let's take a look. Okay, so מנא הני מילי דאמרי רבנן אוקמינהו
אחזקתיה *Mena hani mili d’amri rabanan okminhu a’chezkateh*? Where do we get
this principle that you establish something on its חזקה *hazakah*? You assume
status quo until you know definitely otherwise. So אמר רב שמואל בר
נחמני אמר רבי יונתן אמר קרא *Amar Rav Shmuel bar Nachmani amar
Rabbi Yonatan amar krah*, we learn it from the פסוק *pasuk* by
צרעת tzara'as *tzara’at*. ויצא הכהן מן הבית v'yatza hakohen min habayis, אל
פתח הבית el pesach habayis, והסגיר את הבית שבעת ימים *Veyatza hakohen
min habayit el petach habayit vehisgir et habayit shivat yamim*. The כהן
kohen *kohen* leaves the opening of the house, doorway of the house,
that when he sees this spot of צרעת *tzara’at* and he seals
off the house for seven days. Now how can he declare the
house to be טמא tamei *tamei*? דילמא אדנפיק ואתא *Dilma ad’nafik va’ata*,
maybe as he leaves and comes, meaning he leaves the house and
closes it or whatever, בצר ליה שיעוריה *batzar leh shiureh*, maybe the
spot shrank. So how can he declare it טמא tamei. *tamei* if
he's not directly observing the spot at the moment he's declaring it?
Maybe it's less than the minimum size required to declare it טמא
tamei *tamei*. Meaning from the time he saw it until he leaves?
Yeah, exactly. How do you know that it's still as big as
it was as it was ten seconds ago? So obviously we assume
things are the way you've observed them until you know otherwise. Okay,
so אלא לאו משום דאמרינן *ela lav mishum d’amrinan*, because we say
אוקמינהו אחזקתיה *okminhu a’chezkateh*, establish something on its חזקה *hazakah* and you
assume that it is the way that you've known it to be
unless you know otherwise. So מתקיף לה רב אחא בר יעקב Rav
Achav bar Yaakov, *Matkif lah Rav Acha bar Yaakov*, so רב אחא
בר יעקב Rav Achav bar Yaakov *Rav Acha bar Yaakov* asks and
says ודילמא כגון שיצא דרך אחוריו *v’dilma k’gon sheyatza derech achorav*, maybe
he walked out of the house backwards so he was looking at
the spot till the very last second. Okay, so דקחזי ליה כי
נפיק *d’kachazei leh ki nafik*, so he's seeing it as he's leaving.
So אמר ליה אביי *Amar leh Abaye*, אביי *Abaye* said שתי תשובות
בדבר *shtei teshuvot badavar*, I can give you two answers to that
suggestion why I think it's a bad suggestion. חדא דייציאה דרך אחוריו
לא שמה יציאה *Chada d’yetziah derech achorav lo shemah yetziah*, walking it
backwards is not called leaving. If the תורה *Torah* says he should
leave it means leave the normal way. ועוד, אחורי הדלת מאי איכא
למימר *Ve’od, achorei hadelet mai ika l’meimar*, let's say that the spot
is in a place that you can't see that's behind where the
door is. So even so you can't see it as you're walking
out. Assuming the door is open, right, who says the spot is
right in front of you? Maybe it's maybe if the door jars
open this way and you're walking out like this, right, maybe the
spot is somewhere on a wall over here and you can't see
it even if the door's open you can't see it because it's
blocking it inside the house. So maybe he's not seeing it. וכי
תימא דפתח ליה כוותא *V’ki teima d’petach leh kavta*, you'll say oh
well maybe we'll cut a window into the door so even as
the door's open even if it's behind the door I can look
through the window and see it. So דתנן *d’tenan*, we teach in
a משנה *Mishnah*, בית אפל *bayit afel*, if it's a dark house
that has צרעת *tzara’at*, אין פותחין בו חלונות לראות את נגעו *ein
potchin bo chalonot lirot et nigo*. You don't open up windows to
see it because it says לכל מראה עיני הכהן *l’chol mareh einei
hakohen*, based on what the כהן kohen *kohen* can see. So actually
if there is not enough light naturally
in your house, natural light, to see the
spot, the כהן kohen *kohen*
cannot declare it טמא *tamei*. He can only declare a צרעת
*tzara’at* טמא *tamei* if he can see it based on natural light
and you would not, and if it starts without having windows, you
would not say let's open up a window so that I can
see it. No, you deal with the house the way you find
it. So he'd call it on a cloudy day though, is that
what you're saying? No, that would not be an... no, he has
to wait till like a sunny day? He might be able to
see more? Maybe, I don't know. Okay, but anyway but not, here
it has to do more with the way the house is constructed,
not what, right. אמר ליה רבא *Amar leh Rava*, so רבא *Rava*
says no no it's still a good possibility, I'll answer both your
questions. דקאמרת יציאה דרך אחוריו לא שמה יציאה *D’ka’amart yetziah derech achorav
lo shemah yetziah*, your question, you can't say that you walked out
backwards, that's not considered normal leaving. כהן גדול ביום הכפורים יוכיח *Kohen
gadol b’Yom HaKippurim yochiach*. How about כהן גדול *kohen gadol* on יום
כפור *Yom Kippur*? דכתיב ויצא *Dechtiv veyatza*, it says that he leaves
and we know he walks backwards. דתנן *D’tenan*, right, it says ויצא
אל הבית *veyatza el habayit* I think what's the phrase? רש"י *Rashi*
quotes it, ויצא ועשה את עולתו ואת עולת העם *Veyatza ve’asah et
olato ve’et olat ha’am*. After he removes the pan that which had
the coals and which contained the frankincense he goes back out of
the קודש הקדשים *Kodesh HaKodashim* and says ויצא *veyatza*, he leaves it.
But we know that he walks backwards as he exited the קודש
הקדשים *Kodesh HaKodashim* to not turn his back on the Holy of
Holies. How do we know? So דתנן *d’tenan*, because we teach in
a משנה *Mishnah*, יצא ובא לו דרך כניסתו *yatza u’va lo derech
knisato*, that he exits the way he came in, which is assumed
to mean that he walks backwards as he exited the קודש הקדשים
*Kodesh HaKodashim*. backwards, and that's what we assume by the כהן גדול,
so you see it is considered leaving. ותקמיתיה, v'tekamiteh, your other question
of בית אפל אין פותחין בו חלונות לראות את נגעו, bayis afel
ein potchin bo chalonos liros es nigo'o, you don't open up windows
if you can't see it טפח, tefach, so the גמרא says הני
מילי היכא דלא אתחזק אתחזק, hani mili heicha d'lo itchazek itchazek, that's
before it was established to have a spot and when you weren't
able to see the spot to begin with. אבל היכא דאתחזק אתחזק,
aval heicha d'itchazek itchazek, but when it was established to have a
spot, then I can maybe open up a window so I can
keep on seeing the spot even as I'm walking backwards. So maybe
I'm not prevented of opening up a window. So again, the assumption
was you see that you go by חזקה because you assume the
spot was still the same size, and it says no, maybe you
are actually directly observing the spot as you're leaving. So the גמרא
is still going to rely on this answer. תניא דלא כרב אחא
בר יעקב, Tanya d'lo k'Rav Achav bar Yaakov, we had a ברייתא
braisa not like this idea of walking backwards, which shows that this
is a good source. What's our ברייתא braisa saying? ויצא הכהן מן
הבית, the כהן leaves the house. יכול ילך לתוך ביתו ויסגיר, yachol
yelech l'soch beiso v'yasgir, maybe he can go home and declare the
house to be, you know, to be sealed off? תלמוד לומר אל
פתח הבית, Talmud lomar el pesach habayis, no, he just goes to
the opening of the door of this house, he doesn't go home.
אל פתח הבית, יכול יעמוד תחת המשקוף ויסגיר, yachol ya'amod tachas hamashkof
v'yasgir, if it's the door of the house, maybe he stands under
the lintel? תלמוד לומר מן הבית, Talmud lomar min habayis, he has
to leave the house, עד שיצא מן הבית כולו, ad sheyeitzei min
habayis kulo, he has to actually fully exit the house, he can't
be under the lintel when he's declaring it. הכיצד, haketzad, when does
he declare it? עומד בצד המשקוף ומסגיר, omed b'tzad hamashkof u'masgir, he
stands near the lintel on the outside and he closes it. Okay,
but maybe you're still seeing it, right? You're walking backwards. So now
the key is the next line. ומנין שאם הלך לתוך ביתו והסגיר,
u'minayin she'im halach l'soch beiso v'hisgir, how do you know if he
actually didn't follow this and he actually went all the way home
and he sealed it? או שעמד בתוך הבית והסגיר, o she'amad b'soch
habayis v'hisgir, or even if he stayed in the house and he
sealed it? שהסגיר ומוסגר, she'hisgir u'musgar, how do you know that post
facto it is considered to be sealed and it has its status
even if he goes all the way home? תלמוד לומר והסגיר את
הבית, Talmud lomar v'hisgir es habayis, close it up מכל מקום mikol
makom regardless. So you see, therefore, that if he can declare it
טמא even if he's totally gone home, that we assume that the
spot retained its size and we go by חזקה and he's not
looking at it. The גמרא tries one last valiant effort to undermine
this, רב אחא בר יעקב, and רב אחא בר יעקב would say
back, no, כגון דקיימי דרא דגברי ואמרי כדקאי קאי, k'gon d'kaimi dara
d'gavri v'amri k'dikay kai, maybe there's a row of people from the
צרעת home to the כהן's home and they're doing it and they're
saying it's still there, it's still there, all the way, and he
hears it, so he knows it's there when it's declaring it. Of
course, maybe the time it took for that to travel down the
road... Okay, in the end the גמרא says we see from this
you assume it remained the same size. I want to just say
one last line going back to Charlie's question. תוספות Tosafos says well,
that's to be strict. To be strict, you assume status quo. How
do you know you would assume status quo to be lenient? So
תוספות Tosafos says no, no, no, once we're establishing these principles of
how you deal with doubt, we're not distinguishing between
being strict and being lenient. He also says there's ways here as
well that you're being lenient. You're letting a guy bring a קרבן,
korban, maybe the קרבן korban is not allowed to be brought if
he's not really a מצורע metzora and so on. But anyway, תוספות
Tosafos says it doesn't matter. Once we establish you go by חזקה,
doesn't matter it be strict and lenient. תוספות Tosafos also says how
do you know you go by חזקה even when there's a ריעא,
reisa, even when there's a doubt that, you know, comes up later.
So תוספות Tosafos says well, he has other ways of saying that
because when the כהן comes back, even if the thing has shrunk,
we don't assume that it was shrunk before he declared it טמא.
We assume no, when he declared it טמא it was the right
size and it only shrank recently. Okay, so תוספות Tosafos works out
those details. We've established חזקה. Tomorrow we begin the new topic of
רוב.